Guide to the John S. Daschbach Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
John S. Daschbach papers
1936-1957
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
3050
3050-001
Daschbach, John S.
3.78 cubic feet 9 boxes
Papers of a salesman, teacher, and civil rights worker from Seattle, Washington.
John S. Daschbach was a salesman, teacher, and civil rights worker from Seattle, Washington. He chaired the Washington Civil Rights Congress, the local branch of a national organization organized in 1946 as an association for the "defense of the constitutional rights and civil liberties of the American people, including Communists and Negroes." The Civil Rights Congress, accused of being a Communist front organization, was investigated by the Subversive Activities Control Board and a grand jury. In 1956 the organzation and its branches dissolved. The Civil Rights Congress took an interest in cases which involved Communists or Black Americans whom the National Congress supported with legal assistance, fund raising, and publicity. Daschbach was one of seven defendants who were arrested in 1952 as accused Communists and tried in 1953 under the Smith Act in U.S. vs. Huff et. al. Daschbach was also a board member, extension director, and teacher at the Seattle Labor School (also known as the Pacific Northwest Labor School). His wife, Marjorie Daschbach, was also a board member.
Arranged in 4 series:
Civil Rights Congress (Washington State) records, 1948-1956
Seattle Labor School records, 1936-1949
Personal papers, circa 1940-1941, 1956-1957
Marjorie Daschbach correspondence, circa 1951-1955
The John S. Daschbach papers document Daschbach's activities as chair of the Washington State Civil Rights Congress and as extension director and teacher at the Seattle Labor School. In addition to organizational records, the Civil Rights Congress (Washington State) series includes files concerning a number of civil rights cases in which the Civil Rights Congress took an interest, for example, the Foley Square Trial and the Seattle Smith Act case. Most cases involved Communists or African Americans whom the National Congress supported with legal assistance, fund raising, and publicity. The series also includes information about the the Washington State House of Representatives' Committee on Un-American Activities, commonly known as the Canwell Committee. The Seattle Labor School series includes minutes, correspondence, teaching materials, newsletters, and ephemera from the school. The Personal Papers series includes collected documentation on the Boeing Strike in 1941.
The papers are open to all users.
Gift of John Daschbach, December 1979 and March 1980.
Daschbach, John S.$vArchives; Daschbach, Marjorie; Patterson, William L.$q(William Lorenzo),$d1890-1980; Velde, Harold Himmel,$d1910-1985; Caughlan, John,$d1909-1999; Washington Civil Rights Congress; Seattle Labor School (Seattle, Wash.); Boeing Aircraft Company; United States.$bCongress.$bHouse.$bCommittee on Un-American Activities; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Seattle (Wash.)$xPolitics and government$y20th century; Washington (State)$xPolitics and government$y20th century; Civil rights workers$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$vArchives; Civil rights$zWashington (State)$xSocieties, etc.; Communist trials$zWashington (State); Trials (Political crimes and offenses)$zWashington (State); Aircraft industry$zWashington (State); Strikes and lockouts$xAircraft industry$zWashington (State)$zPuget Sound Region; Civil rights$zWashington (State); Teachers$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$vArchives; Photographs; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); conferences; criminal court records; minutes; reports; Newsletters; writings; Speeches, addresses, etc.; Memorandums; correspondence; Press releases; financial records; curricula; Pamphlets; Petitions; Seattle Labor School News; Labor School News
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Seattle; Washington (State); Labor History; Civil Rights; Photographs; Elementary and Secondary Education
- Civil Rights Congress (Washington State) Records, 1948-1956
  - Organizational Features, 1949, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Outgoing Letters - Appeal Letters, May 1954 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - General Correspondence, 1949-1955 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Memoranda, 1949-1955, undated (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Court Papers, 1949, undated (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Speeches and Writings, 1949-1950, undated (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Speeches and Writings - William Patterson, 1955, undated (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Petitions, 1949 (Box-folder 1/8-9)
  - Conferences and Conventions
    - State Conference of Washington State Civil Rights Congress, 1949, 1951 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Chicago Chapters Secretaries Conference, June 4-5, 1949 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Washington State Peace Crusade Peace Conference, November 11, 1951 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - National Executive Board Meeting, 1950, 1952 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - St. Louis Leadership Conference, June 12-13, 1954 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Congressional Reports, 1948 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - News Releases, 1948 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Newsletters
    - Civil Rights Congress Newsletter, 1949 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Chapter Bulletin, 1952, 1954 (Box-folder 1/18-19)
    - Miscellaneous, 1949-1952, undated (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Publications, 1949-1950, 1952, undated (Box-folder 1/21-22)
  - Directories, 1949, 1951, undated (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Lists, 1954, undated (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Clippings, 1949-1957 (Box-folder 2/3-5)
  - Ephemera, 1950-1955, undated (Box-folder 2/6-7)
  - Photographs of Tule Lake Relocation Center, 1952 (Box-folder 2/7a)
  - Subject Files
    - American Committee to Protect the Foreign Born, 1955, undated (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Canwell Committee
      - Historical Features, undated (Box-folder 2/9)
      - General Correspondence, 1948 (Box-folder 2/10)
      - University of Washington Hearings, undated (Box-folder 2/11)
      - Writings, undated (Box-folder 2/12)
      - Court Papers, 1950 (Box-folder 2/13)
      - Petitions, undated (Box-folder 2/14)
      - Clippings, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 2/15)
      - Ephemera, undated (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Civil Rights Congress (Connecticut)
      - General Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 2/17)
      - Court Papers, [1954?] (Box-folder 2/18-19)
      - Ephemera (Box-folder 2/20)
    - Civil Rights Congress (Pennsylvania)
      - General Correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 2/21)
      - Newsletters, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 2/22)
    - Civil Rights Congress (Pittsburgh)
      - Newsletters, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 3/1)
      - Memoranda, 1954, undated (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Civil Rights Congress (Massachusetts)
      - Ephemera, 1952-1954, undated (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Donaldson (Margaret) Case
      - Historical Features, 1950 (Box-folder 3/4)
      - General Correspondence, 1950 (Box-folder 3/5)
      - Court Papers, 1950 (Box-folder 3/6)
      - Miscellany, 1950 (Box-folder 3/7)
      - Clippings, 1950 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Foley Square Trial (Trial of the Twelve)
      - Historical Features, 1949, 1951 (Box-folder 3/9)
      - General Correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 3/10)
      - Memoranda, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 3/11)
      - Reports (Trial Summaries), 1949 (Box-folder 3/12)
      - News Releases, 1949 (Box-folder 3/13-14)
      - Speeches and Writings, October-November 1949, undated (Box-folder 3/15)
      - Resolutions, 1949 (Box-folder 3/16)
      - Petitions, October-November 1949 (Box-folder 3/17)
      - Clippings, 1949 (Box-folder 3/18)
      - Ephemera, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 3/19)
    - Foley Square Trial -- Rehearing
      - General Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 3/20)
      - Court Papers, 1949-1951, undated (Box-folder 3/21)
      - Newsletters, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 3/22)
      - Ephemera, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 3/23)
    - Forgeries (Crank File), 1951-1955 (Box-folder 3/24)
    - Forgeries (False Want Ads), 1950-1951 (Box-folder 3/25-26)
    - Internal Security Act of 1950 (McCarran Act)
      - Historical Features, 1950, 1955 (Box-folder 3/27)
      - General Correspondence, 1950-1952, 1955 (Box-folder 3/28-30)
      - Minutes (ILUW Protest), 1950 (Box-folder 3/31)
      - Memoranda, 1950-1952, undated (Box-folder 3/32)
      - Speeches and Writings, 1950, undated (Box-folder 4/1)
      - News Releases, 1952, 1955 (Box-folder 4/2)
      - Court Papers, 1950, 1955, undated (Box-folder 4/3)
      - Clippings, 1950-1954, undated (Box-folder 4/4)
      - Ephemera, 1951, undated (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Jones, Mindel, Davis and Other Cases, 1955 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Metaline Miners Strike
      - General Correspondence, 1949 (Box-folder 4/7)
      - Clippings, March-April 1949 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Ephemera, 1949 (Box-folder 4/9)
    - Nelson (Steve) Case
      - General Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box-folder 4/10)
      - Memoranda, 1952-1955, undated (Box-folder 4/11)
        Including petitions.
      - Court Papers, 1955, undated (Box-folder 4/12)
      - Speeches and Writings, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 4/13)
      - News Releases, 1954 (Box-folder 4/14)
      - Clippings, undated (Box-folder 4/15)
      - Ephemera, 1955, undated (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Patterson (William L.) Case
      - Historical Features, 1950 (Box-folder 4/17)
      - General Correspondence, 1951-1954 (Box-folder 4/18-19)
      - Petitions, undated (Box-folder 4/20)
      - Court Papers, April 1951 (Box-folder 4/21)
      - News Releases, 1954 (Box-folder 4/22)
      - Clippings, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 4/23)
      - Ephemera, 1950, 1954, undated (Box-folder 4/24)
    - Patterson (William L.) Tour
      - Organizational Features, 1951 (Box-folder 4/25)
      - General Correspondence, December 1950-February 1951 (Box-folder 4/26)
      - Lists, 1951 (Box-folder 4/27)
      - Miscellany, January 1951 (Box-folder 4/28)
      - Ephemera, 1951 (Box-folder 4/29)
    - Rosenberg Trial
      - General Correspondence, January-February 1953, undated (Box-folder 4/30)
      - Clippings, December 1952-January 1953 (Box-folder 4/31)
      - Ephemera, 1953, undated (Box-folder 4/32)
    - Seattle Six
      - General Correspondence, 1950 (Box-folder 5/1)
      - Petitions, undated (Box-folder 5/2)
      - Clippings, 1950 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Seattle Smith Act Case
      - General Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box-folder 5/4)
      - General Correspondence with John Caughlin, 1952-1956 (Box-folder 5/5)
      - General Correspondence regarding Appeal Drive, 1954 (Box-folder 5/6)
      - Minutes, September 1952, undated (Box-folder 5/7)
      - Financial Records, 1952-1955, undated (Box-folder 5/8)
      - Conferences and Conventions - Emergency Civil Liberty Conference, June 5, 1954 (Box-folder 5/9)
      - Memoranda, 1952-1955, undated (Box-folder 5/10)
      - Speeches and Writings, undated (Box-folder 5/11)
      - News Releases, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 5/12)
      - Newsletters, 1953, undated (Box-folder 5/13)
      - Court Papers, 1952, undated (Box-folder 5/14)
      - Petitions, undated (Box-folder 5/15)
      - Notes, undated (Box-folder 5/16)
      - Lists, [1951-1955?], undated (Box-folder 5/17)
      - Clippings, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 5/18)
      - Ephemera, 1953, undated (Box-folder 5/19)
    - Smith Act
      - Historical Features, 1949, 1951, undated (Box-folder 5/20)
      - General Correspondence, 1950-1955 (Box-folder 5/21-24)
      - Resolutions, 1950-1951, undated (Box-folder 5/25)
      - News Releases, 1950-1953 (Box-folder 5/26)
      - Memoranda, 1951-1955 (Box-folder 5/27)
      - Court Papers, 1950-1951, undated (Box-folder 5/28)
      - Petitions, 1951, undated (Box-folder 5/29)
      - Speeches and Writings, 1950-1951, 1954, undated (Box-folder 5/30)
      - Lists, 1950-1951, undated (Box-folder 5/31)
      - Newsletters, 1950-1954, undated (Box-folder 5/32)
      - Reports, undated (Box-folder 6/1)
      - Clippings, 1950-1956, undated (Box-folder 6/2-3)
      - Ephemera, 1952-1955, undated (Box-folder 6/4-5)
    - Sobell (Martin) Case, 1955 (Box-folder 6/6)
    - Till (Emmett) Case, 1955 (Box-folder 6/7)
    - Velde Un-American Activities Hearings, Seattle
      - Publicity, 1954 (Box-folder 6/8)
      - Appeals, 1955 (Box-folder 6/9)
      - Clippings, 1955 (Box-folder 6/10)
- Seattle Labor School Records, 1936-1949; 1945-1949
  - Organizational Features, undated (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Organizational Information Concerning Committees and Classes, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Minutes
    - Advisory Board, February-September 1946 (Box-folder 6/13)
    - Shareholders, February-July 1948 (Box-folder 6/14)
    - Board of Directors, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 6/15)
    - Staff Meetings, May 1947-January 1948 (Box-folder 6/16)
    - Labor School Forum, Winter 1948 (Box-folder 6/17)
  - Incoming Letters -- Board of Advisors, 1946 (Box-folder 6/18)
  - Outgoing Letters, December 1945-October 1946 (Box-folder 6/19-20)
  - General Correspondence (Box-folder 6/21-23)
    - International Woodworkers of America (Extension Classes), May-December 1947 (Box-folder 6/24-25)
    - Bremerton (Extension Classes), January 1946-July 1948 (Box-folder 6/26-27)
    - Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, International Union (and Tacoma Smeltermen), 1947-1948 (Box-folder 6/28)
    - Regarding Proposed Affiliations, December 1945-August 1946 (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Regarding Finances, November 1947-January 1948 (Box-folder 7/2)
    - Regarding Courses and Instructors, December 1945-October 1947 (Box-folder 7/3-6)
    - Regarding Forums, August 1946-September 1947 (Box-folder 7/7-10)
    - Regarding Social Functions, December 1945-November 1946 (Box-folder 7/11-13)
    - Regarding Dissolution of Seattle Labor School, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 7/14)
  - Financial Records, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 7/15)
  - Financial Records -- Audit Reports, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 7/16-17)
  - Memoranda, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 7/18)
  - Resolutions, 1946, undated (Box-folder 7/19)
  - Curriculum, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 7/20)
  - Reports on Extension Courses, undated (Box-folder 7/21)
  - Speeches and Writings, 1946, undated (Box-folder 7/22)
  - Conferences and Conventions
    - Seattle Labor School Conference, October 6, 1945 (Box-folder 7/23)
  - Lists
    - Seattle Businessmen, undated (Box-folder 7/24)
    - Board of Advisors, Directors, 1945, undated (Box-folder 7/25)
    - Attendance, Registration, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 7/26)
  - News Releases, 1946-1947, undated (Box-folder 7/27)
  - Newsletters
    - Seattle Labor School News, March 1946 (Box-folder 7/28)
    - Labor School News, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 7/29)
  - Teaching Material
    - Agreements/Grievances, 1947-1948, undated (Box-folder 7/30)
    - Labor History, 1947-1948, undated (Box-folder 7/31)
    - Parliamentary Law, 1948, undated (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Shop Stewards, 1948, undated (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Miscellany, 1946-1948. undated (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Clippings, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 8/4)
  - Ephemera
    - Announcements, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 8/5)
    - Seattle Labor School Pamphlets, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 8/6)
    - Labor Songs, undated (Box-folder 8/7)
    - Publications and Miscellaneous, 1936-1948 (Box-folder 8/8-11)
  - Subject Files
    - Cannery Workers, CIO, Local 7, 1948 (Box-folder 8/12)
    - Labor Education
      - General Correspondence, 1946, undated (Box-folder 8/13)
      - Ephemera, 1946, undated (Box-folder 8/14)
- Personal Papers, 1940-1941, 1956-1957, undated
  - Biographical Features, undated (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Subject Files
    - Boeing Strike in 1941
      Despite the fact that Daschbach collected materials about the Boeing Strike in 1971, there is no evidence that he participated in the stike.
      - Minutes, 1940 (Box-folder 9/2)
      - Resolutions, 1941 (Box-folder 9/3)
      - Legal Papers, February 1941, undated (Box-folder 9/4)
      - Bulletins, 1941, undated (Box-folder 9/5)
      - Photograph (Unidentified), undated (Box-folder 9/6)
      - Clippings, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 9/7-15)
      - Ephemera, undated (Box-folder 9/16)
    - International Ladies Garment Workers Union, Local 184: Ephemera, 1940
  - Clippings, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 9/18-19)
- Marjorie Daschbach Correspondence, 1951-1955, undated (Box-folder 9/20)